Good afternoon. Oh, that's loud. I'm
sorry. Good afternoon and thank you for
joining us today for this important
discussion on data center development.
My name is Tom Crave and I serve as the
president of the Cheyenne City Council.
Over the past several months, there has
been significant interest in data center
development within our community.
The purpose of today's panel is to
provide factual information about data
center development, its opportunities,
challenges, infrastructure requirements,
economic impacts, and potential effects
on our community. Our goal is to help
inform the public conversation by
bringing together individuals with
firsthand knowledge and expertise.
We are grateful to our panelists for
taking the time to participate and share
their insights. I would like to
introduce our panel to you now. First of
all, we have Mayor Patrick Collins who
was sworn in as Cheyenne mayor on
January 4th, 2021. Prior to that, uh
Collins served three terms on the
Cheyenne City Council and was elected as
council president four times. Collins
previously served on the boards of the
Greater Cheyenne Chamber of Commerce and
Prevent Child Abuse Wyoming.
Our next panelist is Charles Bloom,
AICP. He is the director of planning and
development for the city of Cheyenne,
Wyoming, a role he has held since 2018.
Charles has over two decades of public
sector planning experience relating to
the development, review, policy
development, comprehensive planning, and
co-development with almost 21 of those
years being in southeast Wyoming. He is
also president of the American Planning
Association's Western Central Chapter.
Next we have Betsy Hail who serves as
the CEO of Cheyenne Leads where she
leads the business attraction expansion
and community marketing efforts. Betsy
has more than 20 years of economic
development leadership experience and
earned her certified economic developer
designation in 2020.
Betsy has extensive experience working
with largecale industrial and technology
projects including data center
development where she has coordinated
the site selection, infrastructure
planning, utility partnerships, and the
management of offsite improvements.
Frank Strong, professional engineer,
serves as the engineering manager at the
Cheyenne Board of Public Utilities. He
brings extensive experience in water and
wastewater system design and operation,
supported by his degree in civil
engineering from the University of
Wyoming and 13 years of prior experience
working as a consultant on water and
wastewater.
His technical understanding and firm
negotiation approach has been integral
in the responsible development of the
data center industry in Cheyenne.
Next, we have Bryce Door, professional
engineer, who holds a bachelor's degree
in chemical engineering and a master's
degree in environmental engineering,
both from the University of Wyoming. He
currently serves as the capital project
supervisor for the Cheyenne Board of
Public Utilities where he manages the
capital and development programs that
ensure infrastructure and resources are
in place to effectively provide water
and sewer services for the city of
Cheyenne. Previous experience as an
industrial process engineer has proven
valuable in understanding and evaluating
the potential risks associated with
on-site data center operations.
Next, we have Austin Allen, who is the
director of data center development for
Black Hills Energy. In his role, he
helps facilitate the development of new
data centers across Black Hills energy
service territories and also maintains
the relationship for our existing data
center clients.
Next we have Jonathan Noble who has been
with Microsoft for over 15 years and
leads state and local government affairs
for energy and economic development
policy in support of Microsoft's cloud
operations and innovation group. Prior
to his current role, Jonathan
represented Microsoft in multiple
western states covering a broad range of
policy areas. Before joining Microsoft,
Jonathan spent 14 years working in and
with local governments on community and
economic development issues.
Next, we have Dan Dioro is vice
president of state policy for the Danis
Data Center Coalition. Dan brings over
16 years of experience in state and
federal government affairs and public
policy. Dan received his bachelor of
arts in history from Boston College and
has a master's in public administration
degree from the University of Colorado
Denver. Then we have Truet Thompson who
was born and raised in Cheyenne. He is
the vice president of the Wyoming State
AFL CIO which represents the building
trades across the state. He brings
extensive experience regarding the
workforce and apprenticeship
opportunities.
We have a great panel. I'm I'm excited
to hear from them. Today we will receive
we have received tremendous response
from the from the public with a total of
84 questions submitted in advance of
today's discussion. Given the time
constraints of a two-hour program, we
reviewed those submissions and
consolidated them into 30 broader
questions that capture the primary
themes, concerns, and areas of interest
raised by the community.
While it will not be possible to address
all 84 questions individually today, all
of the panelists received the complete
list of submitted questions beforehand
to help inform their responses and
ensure that the topics most important to
our residents are represented throughout
the discussion.
To help us keep the program on schedule
and allow us to cover all 30 questions,
we respectfully ask our panelists to
limit their responses to approximately
90 seconds per question. For anyone who
would like to revisit the discussion
later, today's meeting is being recorded
and will be made available for viewing
on YouTube following the event. With
that, let's get started, everybody.
First question I'm going to direct to uh
Betsy and Dan. Betsy, what is attracting
data centers to Cheyenne and why is
there so much growth?
>> Thank you, Councelor Crave, and thank
you uh everyone who's attending today.
This is a great uh turnout and it's a
very important topic. So to answer that
question, why what is attracting data
centers here? Well, number one, it's the
climate. You know, it's 90° out today
and yet the wind is still blowing. And
so that really is a factor in cooling
cost. Um the large load contract for
power that Black Hills Energy, and
you're going to hear about that in a
little bit since 2015 is also an
attraction to Cheyenne and Laramie
County as that's our franchise. Abundant
and reliable power from all types of
generation. And remember, 60% of all
power produced in Wyoming uh is
exported. Um, incredible fiber
connectivity on the internet
superighway. So, most people don't
realize that we have five major trunk
lines that head up I25 and then extend
out across the country on I80 as well.
And so, um, very important to be a part
of that internet superighway. There is a
sales and use tax exemption on servers
and data center equipment. 37 other
states in the United States offer this.
We also have what we call the um data
center cost reduction grant which is
basically a reimbursement of up to 2.25
million of utility expenses that have
already been paid. We also have a very
low risk of natural disasters such as
hurricanes,
um earthquakes, all those kinds of
things. But there are other reasons that
all types of businesses come including
the data centers and that is especially
to Cheyenne and Laramie County is the
access to public water and sewer. Land
use regulations that are clear and
development review processes that are
consistent and predictable. The business
parks or planned unit developments that
are managed and have conditions,
covenants and restrictions. Our tax
policy, there's no corporate income tax
and there's no personal income tax which
is better for their employees. uh our
workforce, both our technical and our
skilled trades people that are here and
our reasonable sales tax, real real
property tax and tangible personal
property tax rates are very reasonable.
>> Thank you, Betsy. Dan, go please.
>> In terms of what's driving growth
nationally, um who has a smartwatch on?
Who has a smart TV at home? Who's got
laptops, phones, Ring doorbells, uh,
garage doors, lights connected to Wi-Fi?
My oven's actually connected to Wi-Fi.
Do I really need it to be? I don't know.
But it's very cool the fact that I could
preheat it when I'm on the road, when I
need to get chicken nuggets in the oven
for my kids after soccer practice really
quickly. Um, we are all driving the need
for digital infrastructure right now.
The average household has 21 connected
devices. Consumers and businesses will
generate twice as much data in the next
five years as they did in the previous
10. Um when it's when it comes to remote
work, online learning, telealth
appointments, electronic healthcare
records, online purchases, 911
geoloccation, state and local
governments, national security, you name
it. Data centers are the backbone of the
21st century economy. They're providing
that infrastructure that allows us to
work, that allows us to learn, that
allows us to be connected. Um, and I
think there's a misperception out there
that all of this growth is simply
because of AI. Um, the reality is is
that cloud is still the major driver of
data center uh development. And that's
because cloud is the underpinning of all
of those things that I just mentioned.
Um, and cloud will be the um dominant
driver of data center development for
the foreseeable future. AI is an
important growth driver. There is no
question about it. But we're not going
to see about an um uh the cloud and AI
even out until about 2035. Um and so the
vast majority of data centers you're
being built uh you're seeing being uh
built and put into operation are to
support our everyday lives in our 21st
century economy. Um and so I think it's
just important to understand the role
that we all play in this growth. Um and
how we are depending on these devices.
is we are depending on this connection
to help us uh work, learn, communicate
and basic and pretty much just be
connected all day every day.
>> Thank you Dan. Our second question will
be for uh Charles Bloom and Betsy and
the question is what is the accurate
real number of data centers being
proposed and or considered in our city
and county? How many actual applications
or permits have been filed? How many
centers are known to be interested in
locating here? And how many center
developments or expansions have already
been approved? And at what level, both
the city and the county? Is it 11, 30,
or 70, as has been mentioned in the
media? Charles,
>> actually, I think you gonna do it first.
>> I think Charles is going to let me go
first on this one. Um, and so I'm going
to try to explain this without making it
too confusing. So at Cheyenne Leads, we
count locations. We don't count
buildings. So you could say we count
addresses or campuses. A data center is
not a data center, is not a data center.
Um, some companies have very large
buildings with very large footprints and
maybe only one building. Some companies
have maybe four to six smaller buildings
on a certain footprint. So it's hard for
us when you say a data center is a data
center and try to count them. So uh our
count is we have 10 that are operating
and this includes everything that we've
had operating since the early 2000s. We
have five under construction. So five
locations that have construction going
on and nine that are announced. They are
in some form of planning. Uh they might
be going through an entitlement process
in the city or county. They might
actually be just going through uh due
diligence before they buy the property,
but we all know that they're coming. So,
um and so it's 10, five, and nine. Since
2020 though, Leadeds has worked with 36
interested data center companies, site
selectors, and developers. And the
reason I say 2020 is that's when I came
to Cheyenne Leadeds, and so I only have
the information since I've been here. We
estimate though that in addition to
those 36 that we have had conversations
with, which by the way, the majority of
those have not materialized. They were
just checking, they were looking, and
then this additional 30 are companies
that have called, they started a
conversation with myself or with
Michelle. And then once we talked about
land prices, salary and wages,
construction costs, construction
materials, uh what we call looks or tire
kickers went silent. So essentially,
you've got 36 that we worked with till
some point where they made a decision
that it was a go or a no-go, and most of
them were no. And then there was another
30 that were just making a quick phone
call. So those might have been real
estate brokers, those might have been
people just looking to see what the
market was like. And once we've talked
about those indicators, land prices,
salary, and wages, and construction
costs, but I would encourage you to
remember that that's today's snapshot.
you know, economic development and our
economy is a movie, right? So, next
Tuesday, one of those companies that
might be uh considering one of the nine
might say, "No, we're not going to move
forward or we might have two more that
are looking that are going to start a
process with the city or the county."
So, just recently, uh, our team put
together, uh, a data center landing
page, and I'm going to try to be slow on
this, uh, at cheyenleads.org.
You can go to our our website and go to
the word Cheyenne at the top and then
you can see there'll be a dropown that
says data centers. And this landing page
will provide for you an updated list of
what we believe the numbers are, but it
will also have information that is
pertinent to all of the things that
you're going to hear about today. So,
this won't be the first time and the
last time you find out information.
We'll be providing that information on
our website. And so grab me after if you
you didn't get the uh cheyenleads.org.
>> Thank you, Betsy.
>> Well, Tom, I'd just like to add that
Betsy did a really really complete job
answering that, so I have nothing else
to add on that on that matter.
>> Thank you. Um, our third question, and
this is directed to Mayor Collins and
uh, Director Bloom. How are city
officials making decisions about data
center proposals? Mayor Collins? Well, I
tell you, I think most of the uh those
decisions are made by technical staff
doing the reviews. Uh planning
department, engineering, building, the
board of public utilities. They're
looking at our regulations. We have
outside agencies like the DEEQ, Black
Hills Energy, WOT, uh looking at
transportation and the environmental
part of it, the power. And then we work
with leads. um they do background checks
on all the companies that we look at uh
to find out what their past practices
are in the communities that they work
in, what kind of behavior they have, are
these the kind of companies that we'd
want to have uh locate here in Cheyenne.
Then I like to meet with them personally
uh to discuss their project and what our
expectations as a community are. And we
share the philosophy with them that data
centers should do no harm. And what I
mean by that is our residents and our
rateayers should not be expected to
subsidize any aspect of their operation.
They must pay 100% of their impact. So
we talk about water and uh one of our
largest concerns uh the requirement that
they must use technology to uh do the
cooling on their site. That could be a
closed loop system. It could be air
chillers. Um but it can't be the old
style evaporative cooling. uh we're not
going to allow that. We uh we talk about
sound, making sure that um a sound study
is done and that the noise shouldn't
affect their neighbors. We talk about
lights and controlling that. So, both
during construction and afterwards, so
they're good neighbors that way. We talk
about traffic in and out of their site
um both during construction and um and
afterwards and what off-site
improvements they might have to pay for
in order to be able to make that happen.
We talk about the power where it's going
to come from. And if it's behind the
meter, are they going to be connected to
the grid? Because if they're not
connected to the grid, that really
reduces the ability for the city and the
county to capture the sales tax and
franchise fee revenue that makes the
data centers profitable for us. Um, and
then we talk about water and sewer. if
uh the revenue to the board of public
utilities isn't going to cover the cost
of the board to maintain them. So, they
have a really long line, but their water
usage is low and the the revenue we're
going to get doesn't cover the cost of
the maintenance that they should expect
to pay an additional fee to cover those
costs. And then we talk about the
council process and how long it takes.
And we could use the Microsoft that's
coming before us on Monday night. Um we
have an application that's coming. Uh
went to the planning commission. Uh
Monday night we're going to have a
public hearing. Uh and then after that
public hearing um it'll be on first
reading and it'll be assigned to the
public service committee. So the public
hearing is an opportunity for everyone
in the community that wants to talk
about that project to come before us. Uh
and then it goes to the the public
service committee. Uh Dr. Michelle
Aldridge will chair that meeting. We'll
get a recommendation from that. It'll go
back to the city council uh for second
reading. again another public meeting
back to the public service meeting and
then a third and final reading at the
governing body. So there's at least five
opportunities for the public to
participate in that conversation.
>> The mayor did a great job talking about
what what goes on with some of the
review administratively in the planning
and development office. We we also look
at each of these applications as they
come in and we're trying to evaluate um
how we make our decisions. You know we
really look at you know what is what is
the tax revenue for this? This is one
item, tax revenue. Um, one thing with a
data center with the footprint, if uh
you're looking at assessment for taxes,
you're seeing about two and a half times
the tax revenue than you would for a
standard retail store big box. What does
that mean? That really helps out the
community because what it does is it
helps fund our general fund, which helps
fix some of roads or infrastructure,
provide those real quality of life items
that we are looking to have here in Col
or in Wyoming, unlike other states like
Colorado where they have much larger
general funds. that can support um those
types of things much more efficiently.
In addition, we we look at the
individual uh development and how how
does it re does it blend into the nearby
neighborhood? How does it blend into the
area and has it had opportunities to
develop elsewhere? In a lot of cases
where these data centers are located or
areas are proposed for industrial,
they're areas where land has been hard
to develop or it's unable to develop
because of very high infrastructure
costs. With the recent demand, these
these type of large developments can
help fund those improvements that can
lead to um additional development and
better development um opportunities in
the community.
>> Thank you both. Our next question is for
uh Director Bloom and Betsy. The
question is, "What transparency measures
exist for applications and proposals?
How can the public find out about
projects?"
Thank you. The mayor touched on this
just briefly with his last answer. Um he
noted that for one of the items, we have
five opportunities for public comment in
front of the planning commission or the
governing body. Um those those are very
open. their planning commission
meetings, their public hearings, their
meetings in the afternoon and the
evening in front of the governing body.
In addition to that, with our
administrative processes, so for
example, when a developer applies for a
site plan for whether it be a new retail
store, restaurant, or even a data
center, um we've um kept up to date a
development map that's available on our
website. Um that development map you'll
frequently find uh posted on on Facebook
or other social media platforms talking
about what's going in in the community.
Um that development map is hosted by
public input which is a
a interface that's actually supported by
data centers. You need data for that. Um
but that has a summary of all our
applications we have in our department.
It has the ability for people to
comment. So you can provide your comment
on that. that it can start a community
conversation.
Um that project information page is
available uh directly from the city
website. Um and it's um also available
if one were just to search connect
Cheyenne. That's it. That'll get you to
that page.
>> If I can add a little bit to that and
you answered that very well. Uh a couple
things. The connect Cheyenne piece I
think is very unique. Uh it's not
something that you find in a lot of
municipalities. We've been talking with
uh other uh colleagues in other
communities about do you have an online
resource where someone can go in and go
connect Cheyenne and then go to planning
and development and then pull down every
project in the community that is going
through some level of public process.
The great thing about it is if you open
that uh particular project then you can
see who the planner is. You can see when
the different um public processes are
scheduled. So from the planning
commission to the first reading with
city council to the next referral to the
PSC and then back and forth. So you have
phone calls. You can also interestingly
enough make a comment right on that site
about the project because in the
attachments you have the entire packet
that the governing body or the planning
commission will see. So you can see the
packet, you can go in and you can make
your comment. What's interesting, and I
don't know how we'll handle this, but
you don't have to say you're a resident
of Cheyenne. You don't have to say
you're a resident of Laramie County. You
don't have to say you're a resident of
the United States. So, there's a very
transparent process in my opinion uh
with that um regarding how we access
information. Have we done a good job of
letting you know that that was available
since February of 2025? Maybe not. But I
think this is an opportunity for us to
continue to reinforce that opportunity.
Um there's also a county landing page.
Uh if you go to our website, the landing
page for the data centers, we have a
direct link to the county land use map
as well.
>> Thank you. Uh the next question is for
Charles and Betsy again.
What is the approval process before
construction begins? Who approves these
projects?
I'll go ahead and start and and tackle
this one first. Um there's there's a
couple of different processes. It's a
process that occurs prior to them
talking to the city. It's similar to
when one wants to go buy a car. There's
a process you you have a conversation
with yourself. You identify what can I
afford? What do I want? And then you go
to the dealership and you just determine
that. Are you going to a dealership
where it's feasible to purchase what you
want? So that's the first conversation.
That's the behind the scenes. That
happens sometimes outside of Leeds's
knowledge as well. But but when it comes
to a public process, there's a couple of
different pieces. There's the
administrative process, which is what
you commonly see for developments here
in Cheyenne. For example, someone wants
to build a new store, a new business,
it's zoned appropriately. They walk in,
they file a site plan application, they
file for a building permit subsequently.
They also uh provide all the information
we need for that. And that's done
administratively and they they build.
What we've seen with a lot of these
larger developments that are coming in
the community is they need to obtain
that zoning. They need to annex to
become in the city. So you're going to
have those those public meeting
processes. So the processes that you
will see uh for a data center that are
the public facing oftentimes the first
time the city knows about it are
typically a zoning and annexation
application which is approved by
ordinance with those five to six
different opportunities for public
comment. Um and then you would see the
administrative site plan approval
process. That process um that we see at
the city is about four to six months. It
it it varies, but typically falls within
four to six months from the day they
come in and file their application to
the day they're issued their approvals
to move forward.
>> Thank you. I'm just excuse me. I'm just
going to talk a little bit about what
happens long before the company makes a
decision on a location and that is
sometimes we'll be contacted by one of
their land development folks. We'll be
contacted by a site selector. We might
be contacted by a local real estate
broker and they'll say, um, give us the
five best locations of this size. Where
could they go? Could they be served by
water, sewer, and things like that? If
they narrow that down and they get a
little bit further down the road,
they'll actually begin just as you would
if you were buying a home or just as you
would if you were buying a ranch at or
something like that, you would begin
some kind of due diligence, right?
Either through your real estate broker
or through your own due diligence team.
And one of the things I want to stress
is that these are global companies for
the most part that we have here in
Cheyenne. And so they do business all
over the world. And so when they look at
sites, they care just like you do about
wildlife. They care about endangered
species, threatened species. They care
about um the um residential
neighborhoods and the proximity. They
care about, you know, they look into
those things like cultural and heritage,
you know, what are the things that we
need to preserve here and things like
that. Um, and so we spend a lot of time
on our team if they've come through our
our portal. We spend a lot of time with
those companies talking about wetlands
and we see what they're doing with their
wetland studies. And so sometimes I
think we don't realize that when they're
making these kinds of investments,
sometimes hundreds of millions of
dollars, if not billions of dollars of
investment. They can't afford to not be
good stewards of the land. They can't
afford to not make good decisions and do
good things because they don't want to
move into a community for one year or
two years or even 10 years. They want to
be in the community for generations
because of the size and the scope of the
investment.
>> Thank you both. Uh Charles, this next
question is for you. Where are data
centers allowed to be built and are
there setbacks?
Yes, there there are setbacks and that
is a kind of a a tricky question because
there's a lot of different places that
data centers can be developed. Um by
right and conditional those are kind of
the two types of uh of approvals we
have. A by approval means they just have
to come into the office and apply for a
permit and they can build. Those are in
our light industrial, heavy industrial,
mixeduse employment, business park zone
districts and also in some of our
specialized zone districts which are
called planned unit developments. We
don't see very many of those today.
Those types of industrial districts,
that's what you see out on in East
Cheyenne around the Lowe's distribution
center. Um you have the area of um the
Meta Complex, you have Northrange
Business Park. Those are areas that are
primarily industrial in nature as well
as areas uh surrounding the railroad
tracks on the north and and south side
as the Union Pacific line flows through
the community. Um there's also the
ability to have an approval through a
conditional use process. That is a
process that requires review by a seven
member board or board of adjustment
which is comprised of volunteers that
are appointed for terms by the governing
body. Um they have a public hearing.
They notify neighbors and neighbors show
up to comment on it and then they make a
decision on whether that use is allowed
at location. That's in a variety of zone
districts. That includes our
neighborhood business district, um our
mixeduse business district, our
commercial or community business
district, our central business district
which is right here in the downtown. Um
and also uh the county land use district
which completely surrounds us in the
unincorporated county.
Um the community business district
that's that's like Del Range Boulevard
uh Lincoln Way that's the community
business district all those could
support smaller data centers but they
would have to go through a public
process. Regarding setbacks they vary
from district to district. Um but there
is a setback that is required for those
um uses. It's typically going to be
dictated um by what they feel is an
appropriate buffer from their neighbors.
>> Thank you. Uh, this next question is for
the mayor, Betsy and Dan, and the
question is, "What incentives or
subsidies exist for data centers? What
taxes do they pay and how much, Mr.
Mayor?"
>> All right. I'm aware of two incentives
for um data centers currently. One is a
sales tax exemption on the servers
themselves. The data centers, they
replace those every few years.
um 30 uh over 30 I think I heard earlier
it's 37 but I know at least 30 states
have a similar sales tax exemption and
it's my understanding that without that
um development of data centers don't
happen in your in your state. The other
one is a Wyoming business council grant.
It's like $2 million that you $2.25 uh
million dollars that you can uh apply
for uh to help cover some of the costs.
And uh to my knowledge right now their
data centers just aren't aren't applying
for it. We've had one I think that I can
remember uh in all my time. After that,
Shine Data Centers have to pay for
everything. 100% of the cost to build
and to operate their their centers. And
we can talk a little bit about taxes.
Maybe I'm not an expert on this, but uh
um they pay property taxes in their
buildings. And uh Microsoft reported
last year that they paid nearly 11
million in property taxes in Laramie
County. They pay personal property taxes
on their servers and their equipment.
They pay sales tax on the electricity
that they use. And this is an
interesting uh statistic for me. We just
finished our budget. We'll actually
finish it on Monday. Since 2021,
Cheyenne's sales and use taxes are up
50%. Um from 21 uh 2021 to today. During
that same period of time, oil and gas
has kind of disappeared. We haven't had
a rig in Laramie County for a long time,
and we've seen between a half a million
and a million dollar reduction in our
sales taxes because of that. We just got
a report uh from April and we were down
$591,628
in oil and gas exploration sales tax,
but yet our sales taxes are up 50% in
that period of time. And then our
franchise fees when you get your
electric bill uh and your gas bill,
there's a 2% fee that if you live in the
city is paid to the city for the right
to work in our our rightway. And that's
what Black Hills remits back to us. That
number is up 125% in the last five
years. and I attribute that to uh the
impact of uh of the data center
development that's happening here.
>> Thank you.
>> If I could if I can follow on on that.
So um again the question was what
incentives or subsidies exist for data
centers? So um Cheyenne Leads is a 501c6
private nonprofit. that we were formed
in 1986 because the Walmart distribution
center that's located at Crossroads
Boulevard down in Lovelin, Colorado
actually wanted to be located here in uh
at the intersection of I80 and I25. And
unfortunately, we didn't have what you
call business parks or shovel ready
sites is what they were looking for. And
so our organization was started in
response to that so that we could start
to have shovel ready sites and business
parks. And so since 1992, we have
provided 16 different companies land for
no cost or at a reduced cost. The Echoar
campus and the first Lunavi data center
both in Cheyenne Business Parkway
business park received land at no cost
or reduced cost. The National Center for
Atmospheric Research Encar and the first
Microsoft data center are both in
Northrange Business Park and received
land at no or reduced cost. I also want
to point out the city, the county, and
the state of Wyoming provided economic
development funds for infrastructure for
the parks. So, the streets, the water,
and the sewer. However, our organization
also held two progress and prosperity
fundraising campaigns to purchase the
land and build some of the
infrastructure. So, there isn't really
one organization or one, it's called the
tiramisu of financing or the lasagna of
financing. It's this is how we do
economic development everywhere across
the country. So the first uh data center
incentive was 2002, but we actually
didn't start the parks for um data
centers. Our first incentive was to see
our trading post, which is the large
distribution center now owned by TJX. Um
but Lowe's, the Arundle Building, the
Walmart distribution center out in North
Range, UMC Technology, TBC
Manufacturing, Searing Industries, and
Eagleclaw have all received land at zero
or reduced cost. So we've built the
parks for all kinds of companies, not
just for data centers. As of 2025, the
return on investment to Cheyenne,
Laramie County, in the state of Wyoming
is $810 annually for every dollar that
has been invested in the land and the
infrastructure in the parks. There are
1971 direct jobs and 14 uh 1411 indirect
jobs in the park. And the annual payroll
in those two business parks is $152
million. Please remember though, we also
manage the bison business park and the
highlains high plains business park, but
those projects are not yet included in
our ROI study, but they will be included
in our 2027 ROI studies, which will
complete sometime next year. Um, in
those two business parks, no incentives
were given to Microsoft or Meta, and
they actually paid uh market rate or
more for the land and the real estate,
and they are paying for all of the
infrastructure uh to those sites.
>> Thank you, Dan.
>> Let's take a step back and understand
why there is a sales tax exemption on
server equipment. 41 states have a sales
tax exemption on manufacturing
equipment. Uh the philosophy being we're
not going to tax the inputs but we want
to make sure that you can operate
reinvest in this facility so that we can
have the economic activity. We can have
the outputs that are taxed. The same
thing is true of data centers. We turn
the servers over about every three to
five years. That's about their useful
life, but it also accounts for
evolutions in technology. The new chips
coming out are something like what 25%
more efficient um energy efficient than
the old chips. So that means we can have
the most up-to-date technology in this
data center to be able to operate more
efficiently, do more with less and to be
able then to keep this facility um open
and running for the foreseeable future
for the long term. So that same
philosophy that applies to manufacturing
equipment. We're going to defay some of
this cost so that you can continuously
reinvest in your facility. That's the
reasoning behind the data center sales
tax exemption. And with that has come we
heard a little bit of some of the local
figures. Um but in 2024 the data center
industry directly and indirectly
contributed 26 million in taxes to
Wyoming state government. We heard 11
million in taxes to local governments in
Wyoming. So data centers are paying
every other tax that comes down with
that. It's just by deferring the one
cost you continue you foster continuous
reinvestment in that facility that puts
people to work that creates jobs. You
foster expansion. It's that economic
activity that data centers generate
which is far outweighs the cost of that
exemption.
>> Thank you. Thank thanks all of you. Uh
Mr. Mayor, this uh next question is for
you. Do local officials sign
non-disclosure agreements or receive
kickbacks for data centers?
I love that question. Thank you. Okay. I
have signed one NDA in my career um
since being elected mayor and that's
with Cheyenne leads um as my job of my
position of being the mayor um I'm
invited to be part of their board of
directors and that NDA has two things
one of them is it requires me to declare
any conflicts of interest that I might
have. So if I've got a conflict I need
to declare that conflict and then it
prohibits me from sharing information I
learn from my board activity. And I
wrote down just quickly uh the paragraph
that I think is most important. It says,
"Be by becoming a board member, I accept
an ethical and legal obligation not to
disclose
to anyone outside leads any information
which could be reasonably considered to
be confidential or proprietary and which
has been gained through LEAD's
activities
unless authorized or otherwise made
public by the business, the industry,
government or other body to whom such
confidential or proprietary information
belongs.
So, what what I take that to mean is if
I'm at a lead's board meeting and I
learn something that's proprietary or
confidential, I've got a I've got a an
NDA on that. But in my job as mayor, the
things that I learn and the things that
I participate in, those are all public.
Uh I have been asked by companies when
they come to talk to me about power and
data uh if I would sign an NDA as a
private company and um u and I' I've
declined. I tell them that I think it's
inappropriate for a public official
working with an uh a private company to
to do that. Whatever I do in my capacity
as mayor with them is a public uh a
public process and I decline that. You
asked about um gifts or kickbacks. Um I
am not aware of any public official
being offered any gifts or kickbacks.
I'm not aware of any public official
that has signed an NDA with a private
company.
I do get allowance from my wife. I don't
know if that counts. and Heidi, you're
five days late or six days late. Uh but
other than that, uh I have signed one
NDA and uh that's only because of my
position as a board member of leads.
>> Thank you. Uh Dan, this next question is
for you. How do data centers affect
property values?
>> So there is no empirical evidence that
data centers reduce property values. But
what I will say is that there is very
clear evidence that data centers can
reduce the property tax burden for
residents. Lowden County has lowered
their property taxes two years in a row.
Lowden counties in Virginia, Northern
Virginia, essentially the data center
capital of the world, largest market
globally. They've lowered property taxes
two years in a row for residents.
They've lowered the vehicle tax rate in
the county two years in a row for
residents. And what do they attribute
that to? data center revenue.
Specifically,
the city, the county manager has said
this is because of data center revenue.
Red Oak, Texas, just south of Dallas,
they have 13 billion dollars of
investment coming in on formally
taxexempt land. This is land in which
they didn't have a revenue stream from
at all. And now they have a significant
sustained revenue stream from this land.
We have a mayor in Covington, Georgia
that says, "Long-term, I want to get rid
of residential property taxes because we
can make that difference up with an
Amazon data center in our community. We
see significant impacts on the issues of
affordability and how data centers and
the revenue and the economic activity
that they generate help to reduce tax
burdens, help to address those questions
of affordability in communities. And so
again, there's no evidence that data
centers reduce property values. Um
Lowden County has some of the highest
property values in the country. Also has
some of the best schools in the country.
1 billion dollars going directly to
Lowden County schools uh in 2026. Half a
billion going to nearby Prince William
County in 2026. These are significant
revenue streams. Um and data centers can
actually help to reduce the property tax
burden and make lives more affordable.
um make life more affordable for the
residents of those communities.
>> Thank you. Director Bloom, this one is
for you. How does data center
development affect future land use?
>> Thank you. Data center developments um
and data centers, they can make land
viable for development that wasn't
viable before. For example, I look at
the meta development of their campus
down south. That area was an area that
was underserved by sewer. It was an area
where we wanted to see growth, but the
infrastructure improvements were so
expensive to get to get a sewer line out
there. So nothing could happen. With the
meta development occurring, a sewer line
extension was made that was significant
and opened up a whole bunch of different
opportunity for development in that
whole area of the community. We see that
in a lot of areas because of the
investment that they make in
infrastructure.
Secondly, in our established industrial
areas, um those data centers that are
being developed, uh they are generally
align aligning with the development
expectations. Um one thing that's unique
with the with the data center
development is that initially with our
industrial parks, they were planned for
uh developments that had a lot more
traffic, a lot more trip generation, and
a lot more emergency response need. Um
as a data center develops, they have a
larger footprint. Um, but they do have a
more privatized footprint as well where
they're being designed in ways where
there's one entity supervising one
structure that generally has higher
security. It's built to higher standards
with fire protection and it's not
generating the heavy industrial traffic
that we used to see in the past. Um,
over time you're going to see a lot less
wear and tear on our roadways. Um,
you're going to see a lot less stress on
our services. So, you're going to be
resulting in efficient um use of that
industrial area. Um with the recent data
center development that we have had in
the community though, we are um
recognizing that we don't have a lot of
industrial land here in the community
that is available for development. Um
primarily our industrial is in areas
along the railroad. We have the business
parks uh to the east. We have north
range to the west. Uh we have the new
meta area to the south. But really we
have a handful of industrial areas which
is why you're seeing a lot of the public
processes where the demand is there for
uh new new industrial areas which is
changing the land use and that is
opening up the door for us to look at
the land use in the area as to what
truly is needed because if we change the
character um in the character of our
industrial land uses, it's going to have
a change in what residential and what
commercial land uses we're going to need
to follow suit with that and as we
develop and you look around the
community of Cheyenne, you start to
notice that right now we have
residential in different pockets. So, we
can really look to continue to um hem
ourselves hem ourselves into areas where
we want our residential areas to grow
and continue to grow so we don't further
stretch our resources that we have
today.
>> Thank you. Uh this question is for
Charles and Betsy. Are impact studies
conducted before data centers are
approved?
>> Uh yes, Mr. Seagra, I'll answer that,
but I wanted to wrap up on Charles as he
he he brought the uh the discussion of
bringing sewer and water and roads to
other land so that it becomes
developable. And I know there's been a
lot of concern and a lot of
conversation. I know one of our planning
commissioners, Boyd Wigum, is always
worried about housing and affordable
housing. And so he always asks me,
"Where are we going to build houses?
Where are we going to build houses?" And
so it's really important that we help
you um understand that when MEDA was
able to help us pay for and complete the
High Plains Road from Highway 85, which
is where the new signalized intersection
is, it's very, it's the biggest
structure for a traffic signal in the
state of Wyoming. when they were able to
help us pay for that, pull that road all
the way over to the new Parsley Road
that goes down south to Terry Ranch Road
that has now opened up uh that 2100
acres. That property owner does not want
to build data centers. He does not want
to build fireworks stands or casinos. He
and his family uh do not want to build
wind or solar. And so we are w we have
worked with them for about a year on
master planning that for future housing
mixed use retail restaurant hotels um
you know and that's a large tract of
land. Now that road isn't open yet but
it'll eventually be open once the Cosmo
or Meta project is complete on
construction. So I did want to let you
know that when Charles talks about the
importance of how does a data center
affect future land use, there's an
opportunity there now where property
owners will be have be able to do things
related to housing and some of the other
needs that we have here in the
community. So as it relates to studies
that we do. So, Cheyenne Leads has two
tools that we utilize. Uh, and then we
do a lot of other things, but our site
stats tool is a tool where we load in
the state's budget, the county's budget,
and the city's budget on an annual
basis. And we understand what the cost
of government service delivery is
because, you know, it's not a 100% deal,
right? When a company moves to your
community, they need services. We
measure 50% of their employees living in
the city so that we can understand the
cost of service delivery to those
employees. And we look at that for the
city, the county, the school districts,
the special districts. And so you don't
ever want to think that something is a
total upside, right? Because there are
costs associated with that. And so when
we look at a project, we'll look to see
is it a negative financial impact to the
city and the county and the state or is
it a positive financial impact? And our
board takes that very seriously. and
Mayor Collins has participated in those
presentations. The other thing we do is
we trust, right, but we verify. So we go
back every two years and we have a
University of Wyoming return on
investment study. And so we ensure that
what we thought was going to happen when
we did the site stats, when we
forecasted it has actually happened or
is happening, right? Because things just
don't happen overnight. It takes about
three years to construct any kind of
building. If you saw Eagle Claw come out
of the ground, if you saw TBC come out
of the ground, uh these data centers
coming out of the ground, but we trust
but verify the buildings themselves
don't actually get on the tax role until
they're actually open for business. So,
you won't see that real property tax.
You will see a waterfall effect. And I
think that's really important for us to
understand. The tax information that you
requested before is available on our web
page. It shows the actual uh taxes paid
since 2012 by all of the data center
companies that have been here and have
come since then. But remember, as these
other units come on, as these other
campuses come on, and when when Meta is
up and running at at capacity, those
those tax revenues will go up uh
exponentially. And so we do an ROI
study. We do a site stats. If they're a
publicly traded company, we'll pull
their K10. Anyone can do that if they're
publicly traded. If they're not publicly
traded, we'll actually have a
third-party review of their financials
from uh a trusted uh CPA accounting firm
to take a look and tell us if they're a
going concern or they're not a going
concern. And I can tell you that my
board and my staff oftentimes say no
long before there's any public process
because they're just not a good fit for
Cheyenne and Laramie County. So, so
yeah, there's a there's a lot that goes
into this and I guess that's why it
takes a long time. I mentioned in
another meeting this could be six years
in the making before you start working
with a company to when they make an
announcement.
>> Thank you, Charles.
>> In regarding impact studies, um we we've
tried to do tried to implement impact
fees here in the community and it's been
a challenge over the last couple of
decades. Um impact fees are really
limited to what the city uh can enforce
and we're looking for a nexus or
relationship between that development
and what type of burden it puts on the
community. Uh, for example, uh,
Microsoft had a new data center that was
built off of industrial road and
identified impact was, well, you're
going to create traffic and Burlington
Trail, that roadway near Sierra, um,
that needs to be improved. And also,
that was pointed out during public
meetings they had prior to that meeting,
prior to that development occurring was
identified as a problem. So the impact
there's mitigation where Microsoft
constructed that roadway and a greenway
um to help serve that development and to
serve the neighborhood. Same thing with
the meta complex. There was identified
impacts that they had. Uh Betsy just
mentioned the largest signal structure,
a fun fact to have in Wyoming. Um being
on High Plains Road and South Kley
Highway, that was an impact um that the
Meta Group had to pay for. there aren't
uh expectations of the city to
contribute to that. Um, regarding
impacts, we do have very limited impact
fees uh that are are put together that
are required as a time of development.
Um, we've had park impact fees for
parkland acquisition and enhancements to
your existing parks that have been in in
effect since the early 2000s. Those
dollars have not changed. We're still
collecting the same money that we did
from uh 2002 today. And that's primarily
because there hasn't been support from
the public to increase those impact
fees. However, we do have public safety
impact fees which whenever a new
development occurs, whether it be a
single family house, a data center, a
coffee shop, a car wash, any of those
items, um they do pay a dollar amount
based on a nationally accepted index
where they pay an impact for public
safety. So, we have those two elements
in for public safety. We have one that
kind of assists with parks. it's a
little bit um that that needs some
improvement but hasn't had the political
will or the public acceptance yet. Um
but we are still um lacking other um
impacts that we could see for um other
other elements of the community. Um, one
item uh that these folks do do is they
do have to uh work with other state
agencies as earlier noted and those
state agencies will look at the
environmental impacts and those those
are uh processes that are done outside
of the city.
Thank you. Mayor Collins, what would
cause the city to deny a data center
development?
>> I think Betsy would tell you we've
probably turned away as many companies
as we've accepted. um you know based on
all the stuff that we've talked about
earlier but specifically to data centers
um I think one of the ones would be them
not understanding our do no harm
standard so when we talk about water in
our requirement that they going forward
have to use technology versus high water
consuming u cooling um if they're not
willing to do the off-site improvements
that are required to be able to support
their uh their subdivision. Uh those are
some of the things that uh would
definitely cause us to uh not want to
deal with the company. If we have uh uh
a company that wants to use behind the
meter, they want island. So if you're an
island, meaning that you're not hooked
up to the grid, you you you have your
own power plant and you provide all your
own power. Um there is no nexus for us
then to collect the sales tax on
electricity and those things. And so for
the city of Cheyenne, um I would not be
in favor of doing that because we're
taking up a piece of land, but we're not
getting the full scope of the taxes that
would support our community. And so that
would be one reason I would not want to
support a data center uh if they don't
want to use our large power uh contract
service, the tariff that protects
rateayers from uh the the cost or the
rise or causes rateayers electric bills
to go up because of investment in
electrical stuff. uh we would not want
to have that company in our community.
Um, if the background check that we get
shows a company that takes advantage of
communities, um, leads does that for us
and, um, you know, if it shows that this
is not the kind of company that's a good
steward, um, I would not want to work
with those folks. Or if it's a if
they're picking a location that's not
appropriate, um, or like as an example,
maybe in the middle of your
neighborhood, somebody wants to put a
gas station and a convenience store um,
and it's not it's not an area that it
should be. Obviously, we wouldn't want
to have that. or if they don't want to
meet our parking landscape setbacks, all
those operational standards that we have
as a community. Uh, a company that
wouldn't want to do that is not a
company we'd want to have in our
community.
Thank you very much. We're going to get
some other uh folks involved now. Um,
this is for uh Frank, Bryce, and Austin.
How do utilities assess if they can
handle data centers?
>> Sure, I I can start there. Um so short
story is we handle them like everybody
else. Um there's no special evaluation
that we do that's that's different than
than any other uh potential new customer
or housing development or or anything uh
that would come to Cheyenne. So um the
first thing that we really look at is we
have a a tool that lists whatever our
peak uh usage is historically. So, it's
not based on what we did last year or
the year before. Uh, it's set on what
our our peak is. Um, and we look at that
uh and compare to make sure does this
new development coming into town put us
up to a potential capacity concern,
whether that's related to the amount of
water that we have from our raw water
supply, uh, our ability to treat the
water at our waste or at our water
treatment plant. Um, and then we do a
similar thing on the wastewater side. Um
and as part of that uh tool that we
have, we include a 10% reserve um that
would lower that ultimate ceiling of
what we could get to. Uh so that's
that's where we are. So even when we get
to where we say we are full and have no
water left, uh we are uh providing
ourselves uh a little 10% buffer uh to
allow for changes, a hot summer, things
like that that that could result in in
higher usage across town. So uh that's
what we do on the water supply uh and
treatment side. Uh and then for the
local um site location uh we have
hydraulic models uh that we use that
evaluates the ability for the existing
infrastructure to get the water to the
site. Uh that's both for what it would
need to operate its its business. Um as
well as is is is there sufficient flow
to uh fight fires? Um and ensure that
that that flow is there and that it's
moving through the pipeline in at a at a
speed at a velocity uh that is low
enough that it doesn't cause any damage
to that infrastructure. So um if we do
that analysis and we find that a site is
insufficient um on any of those levels
uh we reply back to um whatever
development is coming in if that's a
data center or a coffee shop um and tell
them these are the things that need to
be upgraded for your business
development to work here or your
residential development. Um and then
that would be their responsibility to
upgrade at their own cost whatever
infrastructure would be required. Um and
then one thing I I will share just just
quickly here to wrap it up. Um on the
sewer side um a lot of these early data
centers uh did what's it called
evaporative cooling. Um, and part of
that process includes a a water dump
where they essentially just flush out
all of the water that's in that
industrial cooler. Uh, and what we have
found is that that rush of water was
kind of consuming our sewer capacity.
So, uh, we made some changes to our
rules that required them to do something
that's called attenuation where they
essentially take that big dump and they
put it into a, um, an underground
storage vessel of some sort um, that has
a small opening at the end so that that
that large discharge of water is slowly
released into the sewer system which
maintains our capacity, reduces our need
to go and upsize things, allows cause
other developments and things to to come
into that area. So, so we're we're
continually learning and continually
adjusting to things that we're learning
um as we see different types of industry
and development come into town.
>> Uh to add to that, one of our main
philosophy at the BOP right now is it's
not our system. The system belongs to
you, the water and sewer users. So,
anytime anybody comes in, they always
ask, you know, can you do this for us?
Can you do that for us? And I say, "No,
we collect rates to keep the system
operating. If you want to make it
bigger, you've got to pay for it because
we do not want to put that impact onto
our existing customers."
>> Yeah. Afternoon everyone. So from the
electric utility side, we've been
serving data centers in Cheyenne for
over a decade now. Uh underneath our
unique unique tariff format with
Microsoft, our large power contract
service, LPCS service. And the two main
core principles of that tariff and the
tenants of that tariff are to protect
our retail customers and provide
benefits to our retail customers. So the
very first thing we do when we're
looking to facilitate the growth of a
new data center is to ensure that we're
doing those two things foundationally.
That's guiding principle for serving new
loads in Cheyenne for data centers. Uh
beyond that we go through some very very
rigorous interconnection studies for our
transmission system. Uh a lot of
detailed uh planning in terms of
generation and resources that take
place. Our our LPCS tariff requires that
new data center customers pay for any
costs that they cause to the system. So
if new resources are required to serve
those loads, they're required to pay for
those loads. Uh, of course we are very
heavily regulated franchise utility. Um,
so we must make sure that we're
complying with Ferg standards, NERK
standards and then of course the public
service commission. Ultimately uh those
processes take many years to complete uh
before projects uh typically start from
a construction start standpoint.
>> Thank you. Uh the next question is for
Frank uh Jonathan from Microsoft and
Dan. How much water do data centers use
and do we have enough water? May have to
get Boo back in this too, but let's
start uh let's start with uh Frank and
go on.
>> Okay. Thank you. So that's been that
question's been asked a lot. So we did
hand out a fact sheet kind of showing
what the city of Cheyenne's water use is
right now. Last year, the data centers
used around 93 million gallons of water.
Uh when you kind of look at that, that's
about 2% of our water sales. So, it's
it's not a huge number right now. We've
kind of looked at all the uh data
centers that are in the works right now
that were approved or under construction
prior to the mandate to close close loop
and our high-end estimate is maybe we'll
sell another 120 million gallons of
water a year. So, that's that's really
like 6% of our water. So it is not a big
impact to our water supply with the
change of going to closed loop. It's
really significant a real significant
reduction in flows. You know right now
for each one of the buildings not the
campuses but each one of the big
buildings you know we kind of would
guess 3 to 5 million a year in water
sales to that building when they go to
closed loop it drops to like 400,000. So
even if we saw another 50 data centers
that might be 20 million more gallons of
water sold. So it's it's it it raises up
to six and a half percent. So it's not a
big impact. And right now with our firm
yield compared to our current water
usage, we could sell another 2.6 billion
gallons of water a year. So we do have
the ability to handle some growth.
>> And I'll jump in there real quick uh
before we pass it down the line. Um in
terms of the water that's being used out
of our system, I think Frank hit the
nail on the head. We have it under
control. So we have a very good idea of
how much water is there. Um but there is
another component of water that that
does play a factor with data centers and
that's the the water that is needed to
produce electricity. Um that can be a
pretty significant uh number uh an
amount of water. Um it's not something
that is under our direct control. Um
however we are are paying very close
attention to that and what impacts that
can have from a state a regional uh
standpoint. Um, and we've had some of
those conversations with Microsoft to
date. Um, and understand that that they
have that uh kind of in their their
long-term vision as well. And um, maybe
a good handoff to you, Jonathan.
>> Sure. Thank you. Uh, so once again,
Jonathan Noble with Microsoft. Thank you
so much for being here. Microsoft's been
a long-term partner uh, member of this
community 14 plus years now, and we take
that very, very seriously. We also know
past does not prologue. uh our ability
to continue to be here, continue to grow
here, continue to be a member here
requires us to do better and we are
absolutely committed to doing that at
every stage of our uh development and
operations and design. Uh as you've
heard here today, uh that that is a big
process, right? We just simply don't
come in, slap some papers on a desk, and
walk out with a permit and get to go.
There is a lot of design work that
happens. There's a lot of planning.
There's evolution off of that planning.
Uh construction, we have built over 68
million dollars worth of infrastructure
on our dime supporting the community and
our projects here. That might be roads,
uh some of the infrastructure we've
talked about. It's greenways. It's a
wide range of infrastructure that we are
investing in uh as part of our
operations here. Moving forward, we
absolutely plan to continue to do that.
We are looking at design uh that is
best-in-class. We are being encouraged
strongly by the city to make sure that
we are stepping up on that front and
it's a good partnership there. Uh and
then there are processes all along the
way to make sure that we are abiding by
our commitments. Microsoft really
recently made a community first pledge
uh around our infrastructure development
speaking to we will um pay our fair
share and make sure our presence does
not in increase electricity rates for
other rate payers. We heard Black Hills
speak to it earlier. Uh when it comes to
water, we will design projects to use uh
minimal water possible and we will also
work with utilities and other providers
to make sure that they are in a position
to either preserve, capture or um
make more efficient amount of water
equal to the amount that we are using.
We will bring jobs to the community. We
will bring tax revenue to the community
and we heard a little bit about that
earlier. And then we will also partner
with organizations in the community
around um workforce training as well as
just education and other things that are
of importance to the community. That's
foundational for us. As it relates to
water,
as I mentioned, we really look at making
sure that we are designing these
facilities to be more efficient, more
efficient in every iteration. Uh they
are often more efficient than other
industrial users by orders of magnitude.
Uh even our evaporative cooling that
we've talked a little bit about to date,
those facilities only use water for
cooling 10% of the year. The rest of the
90% of the year, the rest of the year,
we're pulling in air from the outside.
It really helps us um manage costs.
Equally importantly, it manages water.
The other piece of it is we also, you've
heard about it, we learn as we go,
right? When there was an issue with how
we were discharging water, we partnered
with the utility to make sure we were
addressing that concern. Part of that
evolution is moving from evaporative
cooling to closed loop systems. And our
future development will be utilizing
closed loop systems which use minimal
water. They don't use water for cooling.
They use water for the employees who are
there, showers, toilets, sinks, things
of that nature. So you're really talking
about water usage in these facilities
that are equivalent of about 20 homes,
not even a restaurant. They're very,
very efficient.
>> Thank you so much.
Sorry about that. All right, I'm going
to round us out here and I'll try to do
it quick. Um,
data centers are amongst the most
efficient water users in the economy. We
use less water than semiconductor
manufacturing. We use less water than
food and beverage production. We use
less water than what's lost to water
leaks in municipal water systems on an
annual basis. That's according to
Bluefield Research. I'm going to rattle
off some stats here. In Virginia, the
world's largest data center market. 83%
of data centers use as much if not less
water than a large commercial office
building. In Texas, data centers were
responsible Texas is the second largest
market in the country. data centers were
uh responsible for uh less than a half a
percent of the state's overall water use
in 2025.
In Arizona, top five market in the
country, not known for plentiful water.
Data centers use less water than sand
and gravel mining. Semiconductors again,
and Arizona has a huge semiconductor
industry. Um
we use less water than craft beer
production in Arizona, and we use less
water than golf courses in the state. In
Elgrove Village, Illinois, just outside
Chicago, another top market in the
country, data centers use less water
than laundromats and car washes in
Elkrove Village. Context is important.
This is an industry that is constantly
advancing design and technologies and
techniques. And what we have definitely
figured out is that closed loop
technologies, the innovative hybrid
cooling technologies, these are not new.
These are not novel. They're being
incorporated into modern designs. We
will continue to advance water
efficiency, but it's important to
remember. Uh there is no
one-sizefits-all method of cooling.
Servers need to be cooled. If they're
not cooled, temperature rises as much as
a degree a minute until the servers
fail. If the servers fail, everything we
rely on goes down. 10, 15 years ago, you
go into a server room, you'd want a
light jacket on. The AC would be
pumping. You can go into a server room
now and be very comfortable in a
t-shirt. We figured out the tolerances a
lot more. We don't make these decisions
in a vacuum. We work with the local
utilities and the local providers to
determine what's the best cooling
technology. Do you have enough water? If
not, what can we do to ensure that we
are not overstressing the system? Should
we go to closed loop? Should we use
airbased cooling? Should we use a hybrid
cooling system? This is an industry that
will continue to advance the ball and
they will continue to also be um uh
positive water contributors to the
community. So restoring water, giving
more back, investing in watershed
conservation or watershed restoration.
The industry is really committed to the
communities to um ensure that they are
uh an efficient water user and a
positive member of the community when it
comes to precious water resources.
>> Thank you very much, Frank. Uh technical
question for you. How is water use
measured and monitored?
>> Uh yes. So every connection going into a
data center is metered including the
fire loops because we have no control
over that facility. Therefore we meter
everything to ensure that we can record
every drop of water they use. Uh
starting about uh 10 12 years ago uh we
started installing smart meters and
gateways. What this does we're no longer
required to go up to the meter and read
the dials to say what the the demand has
been in the last month. We can actually
monitor that real time where we can get
a new reading every hour if we if we
need to and we can set up alarms saying,
"Hey, this one is using a lot of water."
Actually, how many of you have been
called at your house saying, "Hey, you
might have a leak and you should get it
fixed." You know, we're very proactive
in monitoring the water usage to ensure
that no one is wasting it.
>> Thank you.
We were talking about water usage and I
turned my sprinklers on recently. So,
it's a big hit at my house. Um, Frank
and Bryce, the next question is, uh,
where does water for data centers come
from? How are we protecting our water
resources?
>> Yeah, I'll start that off. So, um, 70%
of our water essentially comes from the
Colorado River. 15% is from our local
Crow Creek runoff into Granite and
Crystal and 15% is uh groundwater. As
Bryce mentioned, every time we have a
new customer come in, we evaluate their
impact onto our system. Can we handle
them? Can we still facilitate growth?
And honestly, we've told people, "No, we
can't meet your demands. There is just
no way." So, we just monitor it. you
know, we we evaluate it with every
customer that comes in to ensure that we
have a long-term growth potential.
>> Yeah. I I think the only thing that I
that I'll add to that um is that we we
don't live in a silo. We we pay
attention to everything that's going on
around us from national trends, uh
especially the stuff in the west with
the Colorado River. Frank mentioned, uh
what a huge component of our water
supply that is. Um a and we really try
to think outside of the box in terms of
what solutions do we have to help
protect us uh to make sure that we have
water. Um I think a lot of the stuff
that we've done in the past has really
set us up for success. Some of the uh
conservation efforts that we did back in
the early 2000s bringing on our recycled
water system. a lot of the stuff that
you all do at home in terms of uh low
water use appliances and fixtures and
being aware of what how you're using
water. We have grown as a community
by I don't know what the percentage is,
but our our water our water use is
actually declining year after year. And
that and that is really a testament to
you all and you being stewards of the
water as well. Um, and I just want to
let you know that that that we value
that. Um, and we will protect you guys
as you have been protecting us over the
years uh to make sure that we do have uh
a reliable water supply uh for you
moving into the future.
>> Thank you both. Uh, this question is for
the mayor, Frank Bryce, and Jonathan.
Are data centers required to use closed
loop systems? How much water does that
take?
Well, I can start off um as you've heard
earlier um our original data centers
used the more traditional evaporative
cooling methods and um maybe in some
other parts of the country that would be
copious amounts of water but with our
cool climate here uh I think you heard
earlier it was 10% u the number I have
was 37 days a year that the cooling
system has to be turned on uh because of
our our nice weather but today we do
require uh data centers to use
technology to pool. Um, and that could
be a closed loop system or other
technology. I don't know what the future
looks like. So, we're not requiring
closed loop systems, but it's got to be
a technology that's water efficient. I
think Frank and I had a conversation, is
it earlier this week or last week? A
company wanted 2.5 million gallons um a
day to cool a manufacturing process.
There are other technologies to do that
and we respectfully said no. Um, so we
do require that. Uh I did meet with a
data center company and a man a person
that's manufacturing putting a closed
loop system into uh a a Cheyenne data
center and they both told me the same
story and that is um that their closed
loop system requires about two acre feet
of water to charge the system. So once
it's built and it takes about two uh two
acre feet of water apparently they put
some glycol in there. I'm not sure
exactly how that process all works, but
they mix some glycol in there and then
they can recirculate the water up to
maybe six years. And uh so we talk in
acre feet and we've been told that
that's not the the terminology that the
public likes to use. So an acre foot of
water is 325
851 gallons of water. So two acre feet
would be 651
702 gallons of water and that's what it
takes to charge the system.
Uh, an Olympic swimming pool uses
660,000 gallons. So, basically it's an
Olympic swimming pool of water that
fills that system. Um,
maybe to give some balance to that, uh,
a single family home uses a quarter of
an acre foot of water a year, 81,000
gallons of water. Um,
I think Bryce or Frank said a little
earlier, we have 22,000 acre feet.
That's how much water we have every year
in our bowl to drink. And we use about
12,000 of that. So, we have 7 billion
gallons of water that the city of
Cheyenne has to sell every year. And we
sell about 3.9 billion gallons if I got
my math right. I wasn't a math major in
college, but I tried to do the math. Um,
and so once it's charged, as uh Jonathan
said earlier, then uh I look at these as
being like an office building. uh you
have domestic uses, you have your
bathrooms, your coffee makers. Um if you
have some ir uh some landscaping
outside, you might irrigate some of
that. But that's the uh uh that's the
extent of the water use after that. So
um the the question I keep getting asked
is what happens after that six years or
so? What the companies tell me is they
have a provider that would come in and
they bring that water out and take it to
a certified facility to dispose of it.
and then the system's flushed, refilled,
and then it's used again for six years.
And so, uh, to answer your specific
question, Mr. Crave, we do require
technology, and closed loop is one of
those technologies.
>> Thank you,
>> Jonathan.
As I mentioned earlier, we're committed
to being more and more efficient with
our water use. We've talked about the
strategies involved. Um, closed loop is
definitely part of the strategy we're
using moving forward. Uh for those of
you who attended any of the open houses
we've had um or the open house we've had
as well as some of the other community
meetings we've had, you know, we're
committed to that. That is a transition
Microsoft is making across our portfolio
to especially here in Wyoming where we
are moving to closed loop systems uh in
combination with air chilled coolers. Uh
these systems are wellestablished
technology. They've been used in the
industrial uh format for a long time.
Shoot. They've been used in our homes uh
for those of you who might have radiant
heating and or cooling uh for a number
of years. Well established technology,
new use case for it. It's been very very
successful and we're looking forward to
making that transition to that use case
here. Uh we do all of this in close
partnership with utilities. You've heard
about the level of planning that goes
into the system, the improvements, etc.
to make sure that the designs we are
implementing are working in conjunction
with the planning that they're doing,
the designs that we uh develop uh to
make sure the systems are whole, not
simply, you know, at our property line,
but throughout the entire city. And we
make investments to make sure that our
systems are not raising costs, not
impacting other uh consumers, whether
that's from a rate perspective andor a
operations perspective. We are as
reliant on these systems as you all are
and we are deeply deeply committed to
making sure that they work uh now and
into the future.
>> Uh guys from BOPU any additions?
>> Something real quick. Um I I will echo
the the closed loop system is not
something that's new and fancy and
cutting edge. Um I'll admit that when I
first heard it I didn't know what it
was. Um, so, uh, a little bit of, uh,
internet research to educate myself. Uh,
I was able to understand a little bit
more of what they are, things that we
can look for, um, and that type of
thing. So we'll talk a little bit more
about it later in the wastewater uh
realm, but there are things that we are
learning as I said and and developing
new rules and things to to make sure
that this this different technology than
the the evaporative cooling uh we're
also uh protecting um our systems and
you all
>> um you know the question is is how much
water they going to use right now with
the domestic demand and then you know
potentially have to flush the water
every six years is kind of a number
we've been hearing. Um we really expect
each building to use about 400,000
gallons of water a year. That's
equivalent to right now what is five
homes in Cheyenne. You know, not every
home has a big yard, but some do and
there's a lot of irrigation. Some don't,
but on average that's five homes. So,
it's not a large amount of water when
you compare it to a single family home.
>> Yeah. And just one thing to add on to
that real quick. So, the the six-year
maintenance cycle flush thing, we've
heard uh variations of what that can be,
3 to six years. Just so you all know,
and when we put these numbers together,
we use the most conservative every
three-year approach when we're looking
at the total amount of water that's
used. Um, and then again, to reference
back to what what Frank had said
earlier, we do monitor uh each one of
these sites through meters. So, if there
are any leaks or major issues, that's
something that we would be able to
identify and and work with that customer
to to make sure that we're not wasting
water that um is not being used
beneficially.
>> Thank you. The next question is for
Frank and Bryce. How is wastewater being
addressed and monitored?
>> So, on the wastewater side, um there's
really two ways that we've looked at
this. uh the evaporative cooling piece.
Uh we talked about the attenuation and
the potential capacity and maximizing
our systems as much as we c as much as
we can. Um on that side, there's also
something um to be fully transparent
that um we have come across with our new
local limit study that that we uh
developed for our wastewater treatment
plants. um has actually reduced the
amount of dissolved copper that we can
release from those plants. Um so we are
now having to work towards reducing the
amount of copper that we take into that
plant. Um some of the places that we
have seen some of that stuff is from our
evaporative cooling uh sites. Uh they
have a lot of copper tubing that moves
the water through. When that sits there
for a long amount of time, for the days
that we don't actually cool it, uh some
of that that copper can dissolve into
the water, um it's not an alarmingly
scary number. We see very similar
numbers um on residential discharges. Um
but in early discussions um with
Microsoft specifically, uh we we are
starting towards moving towards a
solution and how we can address that. Um
it's kind of a partnership up in town.
Um and then on the closed loop portion
uh we have established rules that
that force that require that the cooling
loop and any of the uh glycol any of the
water chemistry the chemicals that are
put into that water to help it you know
maintain its effectiveness for longer to
be more water efficient. that those are
completely segregated from the public
sanitary sewer system. So whether that's
uh spillage, floor drains, all of that
that has to be collected in an entire
different uh system that then gets
pumped and transported to uh the
appropriate facility that is set up to
be able to treat that kind of waste
water.
>> And when it comes to monitoring, we
actually have a whole group that is
dedicated to that. We have an industrial
pre-treatment program that monitors all
industrial users in Cheyenne. So they go
out and collect samples. They monitor
grease interceptors. They're making sure
plumbing is proper. So we have an entire
team that their whole job is to monitor
the sewer flows coming to the wastewater
treatment plants.
>> Thank you.
We're almost done with the water
questions here. Uh we have one more. Um,
this is for the mayor, Frank, and Bryce.
If water is curtailed or limited, will
data centers be affected? Mr. Mayor, I
can share with you that uh when we
talked to some of the uh the data center
companies and they're making billion or
multi-billion dollar investments, they
would like to be treated differently
than uh than everyone else when it comes
to the subject. But as uh Bryce said
earlier, we treat every uh customer of
the Board of Public Utilities the same.
The way we look at them when they come
in to uh apply for water usage and we
treat them exactly the same when it
comes to a curtailment. So if we were to
be told by the Colorado River folks that
we had to reduce the amount of water
that we're going to get, they will have
the similar uh impact as uh as every
other uh rateayer as I understand it in
our in our system. And we've shared that
with all of the private meetings uh from
the first meeting to the last until they
sign and they build their data centers.
They're all aware of that. I will share
with you though some optimistic news.
For the last five years, we've worked
really hard to try to find uh new water
resources to replace the water in case
we do have a curtailment. We have some
very good opportunities at this point.
However, we haven't got anything signed.
Uh but I'm pretty optimistic that we're
not going to have to make radical cuts
in the future. And um I hope that that
turns out to be true.
So let's say we have a curtailment next
year. What's going to happen? So right
now the BOP with all storage and we
don't do any reduction in flows, we
could last four years. Granted at the
end of those four years, our reservoirs
are completely dry. So obviously we're
going to have a staged approach to water
conservation for a long-term
curtailment. Our current plan which we
are in the process of updating starts
with outside irrigation and non-revenue
water and then moves down from there. So
at at some point you know the the data
centers are going to follow that same
process where they're going to have to
reduce outdoor water use then they're
going to start uh reducing indoor water
use just like you as residents would
have to. So we're going to treat
everybody the same and we will survive
the curtailment.
Thank you very much. All right. Uh the
next question is for Austin, Jonathan,
and Dan. How much electricity do data
centers use?
You know, data centers really come in
all different shapes, forms, and sizes.
So, it's we discussed earlier, we've
been serving data centers in Cheyenne
for well over a decade now. Um and we
have users that use data centers that
use, you know, a half a megawatt.
something that's equivalent to a school
or a commercial office building. And we
see data centers that uh want and desire
to use several hundred megawws. And so
they they really come in all different
shapes, forms, and sizes. Um Jonathan,
what would you add to that?
>> I I think you covered it. Uh data
centers do use a significant amount of
energy. There's no question about that.
It takes a lot of energy to power the
critical infrastructure we all rely on.
I know Dan kind of outlined uh the
various ways we all rely on it every
day. Similar to a lot of uh critical
infrastructure that requires investment
that requires reliance on other critical
infrastructure including electricity. I
think the biggest um point to make here
is the one that was touched upon
earlier. the rules and regulations about
uh adding new load to the grid are
really really strict. And it's not
simply a contract between Microsoft and
Black Hills. It's that contract. It's
the contracts and regulatory oversight
that they have at the federal level um
several times over, at the state level
several times over. And we are subject
to that as well. We are absolutely
committed to making sure that the grid
remains resilient uh has the capacity
necessary not simply for our uses but
for everybody's use. An unstable grid is
not something that is to our benefit. We
are probably you know as committed to
making sure that that grid is stable as
any other user out there. Our ability to
operate depends on it and we are making
investments to make sure that the grid
does operate efficiently, does operate
effectively, that there is sufficient
capacity and that we are not shifting
any cost to other rate pairs.
Well, let's go back a little bit to
understand why we have data centers.
Back in the day, we all used to have the
tower computers. Um, or we had a server
closet in the basement of a building or
somewhere in your building. I can
remember one that we had in our office
where the door was half hanging open and
the cooling alarm was constantly going
off. It was either too cold, too hot,
too cold, too hot. It's extremely
inefficient. What we figured out is that
by aggregating our increasing computing
demands together, we can leverage
economies of scale to achieve
significant efficiencies.
So from 2010 to 2018, which is as we saw
kind of really the the larger scale
migration to cloud,
computing output rose 550%.
Energy consumption only rose 6%. So this
is a far more efficient way of doing all
the computing processing and storage
that we need. And yes, we're in a much,
you know, higher growth period than we
were from 2010 to 2018. But the
principle still holds true because right
now, as I explained, you know, this is
all of us. The electricity needs of data
centers are reflective of demand. They
are reflective of this demand curve that
we have been on for really a long time.
But you know, if you look at most maps,
you'll start to see the steep curve
start in about 2020. Even though, you
know, throughout the 2010s, we had it.
But we are on this steep demand curve.
In our ability to meet that, we are far
behind meeting that demand curve. That
means we don't have enough data centers
to meet the demand that there are that
is out there. That means that we do not
have enough data centers to store our
all of our data here in the US safe and
securely. As of right now, we have an 11
gawatt shortfall from in 2025 according
to Goldman Sachs. That means we need 11
more gigawatts of data center capacity
to meet the current demand that's out
there. And we have that huge gap. And a
gigawatt is um uh a thousand megawatts.
So data center demand and data center
electricity use, it's significant. Yes,
it is. But it's reflective of the
economy. It's reflective of national
security. It's reflective of global
economic competitiveness. There are
other countries out there building this
so that they can lead the world in
advanced technologies and they're
building energy infrastructure to go
along with it. Um, and so we will
continue and the data center industry is
continuing to invest and put steel in
the ground to meet that demand. And with
that comes a unique opportunity to
invest in the energy infrastructure to
meet that demand. And I think it's
something where Wyoming is especially
poised to play a critical role in that.
We'll get into that probably here in the
next question.
>> Thank you all. The next question is for
uh Austin and Jonathan. Do we have
enough electricity for data centers?
Yeah, one of the unique things about our
LPCS service which we utilize to serve
data centers is that it requires data
centers to partner with the utility to
bring their own capacity resources to
serve them. So if we are adding new and
additional data centers to the
footprint, we also must plan for and
build new generation resources to serve
those data centers. What I really want
to flag and highlight with that is again
it's a core tenant and principle of the
tariff to protect retail customers and
provide benefits. So the resources the
generation resources that we utilize to
serve retail customers like this w
building we're in right now or your
homes are very different than the
resources that are utilized to support
Microsoft's load or the upcoming meta
load. Um, and so while we continue to
see data center growth occur, yes, we
thoughtfully, purposefully,
intentionally plan with our customers to
make sure that we're bringing enough
resources online in order to serve them
reliably. I think the other thing I'd
like to highlight is Cheyenne for the
last several several years is
consistently rated as one of the most
reliable utilities in the country. Um,
by and large that's significantly due to
the partnerships that we have with data
centers because as we're adding these
loads to the systems, data centers are
paying for significant investments
themselves which therefore also benefit
the reliability, the grid reliability of
our local system here in Cheyenne. And
it's one of the reasons why we're again
consistently one of the uh most reliable
utilities in the country.
The only thing I would add is that
Wyoming is an energy state. Everyone in
this room recognizes it and I will say
that extends to the leadership
that the state has had on partnerships
to data centers. As was just outlined,
we are being held accountable. We are
making sure that we are making the
investments necessary for a strong
resilient grid and we are doing so in a
way that does not impact your rates.
that is the due to the leadership that
the state has had on this issue not
simply over the past five years as it's
kind of grown to be top of mind uh for
all of us but over the past 10 15 20
years uh we fully expect that leadership
to continue uh due to the partnerships
and leadership of folks uh both around
this stage but also uh around this city
and around this state
>> and I'll just add and just build on this
again which is that Wyoming has a
commitment to energy infrastructure. It
has the expertise. It has the workforce
and it has the resources for energy
infrastructure
that sends a long-term signal for
predictability, certainty, reliability
to be able to have a reliable, resilient
electricity grid. It's one of the
reasons why data centers are looking at
Wyoming right now and investing in
Wyoming. It's one of the reasons why
Microsoft was ahead of the curve and has
been here for a very long time. Um
you know we are in a pivotal moment
right now. We just had you know in
general right as we look nationally
about 20 years of flat load growth. Now
we have load growth on our system. It's
from data centers. It's from advanced
manufacturing the policies that have
brought manufacturing back to the shores
here. We have increased electrification.
Um and we have emerging hydrogen
production. All of this is coming
together now. Um and so we are in a
period of high electricity low growth. I
think I think it takes a philosophy to
say we can do this. We can build it and
we will foster economic development, but
we can also do it responsibly. Wyoming
checks off all those boxes. And I think
it checks off all those boxes more so
than a lot of other states that have all
of those pieces in place to say our goal
is not to say we can't do it or we will
limit it or no, we will figure this out.
We will build it and we will do it in a
way that adheres to our values and make
sure that we protect our rateayers. This
is a tremendous opportunity for
investment in in the grid. What we see
throughout the country, large loads like
data centers put downward pressure on
rates for others. Indiana Michigan power
really strong growing market. We're
going to uh lower our rates for
residential rateayers because we have
data centers uh revenue coming in.
Georgia Power, three-year rate freeze,
lowering rates after those three years
because of large loads coming in. The
most significant of which is data
centers. DTE uh energy, Detroit,
Michigan, we don't need a rate increase
because we have two data center projects
come in. And that's our commitment to
you is that these projects come in, we
are not raising our rates. PG&E in
California of all places, not a place
known for cheap energy or commitment to
anything. Um PG& is the largest uh
utility there. We've kept rates as much
as 11% lower because of data centers. We
have a tremendous opportunity here to
help address those uh affordability
questions and keep rates low. Data
centers are playing a key part in that.
And you have the right type of system
set up to ensure that data centers pay
their own way. They pay their full cost
of service and no other rateayers are
affected if but if you're affected in
the positive way, which means your rates
go down because data centers are bearing
the burden of this cost.
>> Thank you, Austin. This is kind of a tag
on there. Uh the question is, "Will my
electric rates go up? What protects my
electric rates?"
Yeah, to to echo what Dan was saying
there, uh data centers will not and do
not increase your electric utility
rates. Um in the last decade, Cheyenne
Light has had one rate case. Um what we
see and to echo Dan's statement is data
centers actually stabilize rates. they
provide far more benefits into the
system from a cost perspective than they
take out and they actually work to lower
rates. Um what protects that from taking
place? It's our tariff. Our tariff
requires that any cost that data centers
cause they must pay for and they must
pay for directly. Um that tariff is
actually codified in state statute as
well. So it's a requirement of the
tariff that we perform this way as a
utility. It's also a requirement under
the service mechanism that we use to
serve large data centers. Uh that's
written into state law as well.
>> Thank you very much. We're going to
change direction a little bit. Um this
is for Charles and Dan. If
contamination, air quality degradation
or other environmental harm happens due
to data centers, who is legally and
financially responsible? How would this
be enforced?
Dan, I'll go ahead and start with this
real quick. From a city standpoint,
we're really looking at a couple of
different items. A lot of the stuff
mentioned in this like air quality and
other environmental um aspects, those
are those are handled by other
departments um at the state level. For
example, state DEEQ, Department of
Environmental Quality, they'll be
looking at at air, any any emissions,
those types of items. state engineers
office. They're going to be looking at
any uh water related items when it comes
to drilling a well if one was going to
do do a development in the
unincorporated county not on city water
or if they're proposing an injection
well. Um the items that we would look at
for any type of enforcement here in the
city are items such as uh site plan,
building codes, making sure that they're
meeting those. And if there are
violations at that municipal level, we
would go through our our general
enforcement process.
Data centers do not get a pass on the
same rules that every other
industrialsized development has to
follow with regard to air, with regard
to water, with regard to soil, with
regard to environmental sustainability
or environment or environmental
protection. I think there's a perception
out there that data centers can simply
do whatever they want. That is the
furthest thing from the truth. There are
built-in enforcement mechanisms because
data centers have to get permits just
like any other facility just like any
other development. Um um as Charles
mentioned, air is regulated by the EPA
down through the state department of
environmental quality. Data centers have
to follow the same air permitting rules
when it comes to both the facility and
backup generation that every other um in
um similarly sized facility has to
follow.
They do not get a pass on this. If a
data center commits a violation, they
have to pay the fine.
There is enforcement. There are permits.
These are the things that are built into
the system here. Whether you be a data
center, whether you be a manufacturing
plant, whether you be a distribution
center, whether you just be an office
building that protect the environment
and ensure that companies are held
liable for violations of existing
environmental protections.
Thank you. Uh Charles, this one is for
you. How is noise monitored? What are
the rules and how is it enforced?
Good question. It's been one of concern
uh greatly. Um we have a couple of
different uh policies in place that we
work with our our data centers and any
development that might make noise.
Essentially, if we have a development
that is going to have property that has
large property or small property, we
look to have that developer prove that
at the property line they are not uh
exceeding 70 dB during the daytime in
industrial district and 65 dB at night.
Um if you're uh close to a residential
area that decreases by five dB down to
to um 60 in the daytime and 55 in the
night time. So those are are what we
have found to be generally acceptable
levels throughout the nation regarding
sound. We have had some instances of
some uses where they have been loud
unfortunately loud. Um we've talked with
those folks directly. who started
enforcement processes with some folks as
well and we've been able to communicate
with them in ways to bring those noise
levels down to acceptable levels. Um but
really what we're looking at is we're
making sure that on a consistent basis
that those are not being disruptive to
zone districts, primarily the
residential ones outside um of that park
or near those uses. When a data center
comes in, they're required to provide a
sound study. uh a study that says this
is what we intend for the sounds to to
be. Um and others have gone as far to
install equipment on their site that
actually provides readings to
demonstrate that's where they are at. We
do have some exemptions that are in
place. Uh those exemptions are for uh a
lot of the generators for backup power
that aren't really needed as much here,
but they do require testing. We have
some pretty strict uh testing
restrictions that they can only test
during uh normal daytime hours for
periods not to exceed 30 minutes for
those units. So, we put a lot of
safeguards in place. I mean, again, uh
we're continuing to monitor um how those
uh regulations are playing out in real
life. Is it something that's working? Is
it something that needs to be revisited?
But so far, uh, it seems like we have a
a pretty good level right now on a lot
of our data centers and monitoring their
sound.
>> Thank you. This next question is for
Frank, Bryce, Austin, Jonathan, and Dan.
Uh, will there be public reporting of
regulatory compliance?
>> Um, yes. So, the Board of Public
Utilities is a public drinking water
system. We are required to provide
public notification. Every year we send
out a a uh consumer confidence report
that talks about our w water quality and
what we're producing and delivering to
US citizens. And then of course if we
have a significant issue, we're required
to do public notification. A couple
examples is um I wasn't here at the
time, but I've always referred to as the
Mother Day incident where we thought we
had a possible contamination of what was
it?
Crypto. Um so we kicked out a public
notice saying you need to boil your
water. it's unsafe.
As we did more research, we found out it
was an a lab at or a lab error, but out
of abundance of caution, we kicked out
that notice so you guys know that
there's a potential issue with the
water,
not cryptocoin. And then um most
recently, an example would be in regards
to our lead levels. Uh as you know, the
EPA has mandated that lead services be
removed and they've increased our
monitoring and and additional
requirements. And was it eight months
ago, something like that, we did kick
out a lead exceedence wart uh uh warning
to everybody in the city of Cheyenne.
So, yes, there will be public
notification from the BOP.
>> Uh the one thing that I'll add to that
real quickly, um we kind of referenced
the the copper issue earlier. Um if that
does become something that is
significant um Frank referenced the our
industrial pre-treatment program uh they
they can classify a business as a
significant industrial user. Uh if that
classification is met uh they are
required to submit self-monitoring
reports um throughout the year um and
then that also in would require us to go
out and do self-sampling as well. Um,
while those we while we don't distribute
those to the public, um, they are
available. Um, if anyone would ever need
to see one of those,
>> we we've heard just a touch upon how
this industry is regulated. Dan spoke to
it. We just heard about what's happening
at the local level. That level of
regulation happens at every single
level. You know, we are subject to
permits that have requirements. If
there's a oftentimes the requirements
open the doors to inspections whenever
the folks want to. It also requires us
to do reporting. We comply with the
requirements in those permits. Uh
sometimes the requirements change
because you know the agencies that are
serving us have changing regulations
there and we have to comply to those
changing permits. We we do we make the
changes required to um comply in terms
of the reports as was touched upon these
are public agencies. These are typically
publicly available uh documentation. So
yes it's public yes there's strict
enforcement and yes we are committed to
absolutely complying with these
requirements. Yeah, I don't know if I
really have much to add be to add beyond
that besides, you know, there is so much
layer of public information within this
because it's a requirement under law
that these permits be available for
inspection. Um, you know, just like
anybody could probably, you know, pull
your building uh permit if you're doing
a renovation on your home. Same thing is
true for data centers. So it's important
to keep in mind that there is a plethora
of information already available within
the system um because we have to have
disclosure because we have to have
regulatory reporting for all these
different requirements.
Yeah. And lastly as a utility of course
we're we're reg regulated from a federal
standpoint and from a local standpoint
what the public service commission um
it's very detailed. I I can say for
instance one of the things that we go
through on an annual ba basis and again
it's just the assurance and shoring up
that we're providing the lowest cost of
energy to our base retail customers
versus our data center customers. That's
an audit that we go through on an annual
basis just to ensure that that is in
fact the case.
>> Thank you all. Uh the next question is
for Mayor Collins and Director Bloom.
What would cause the city to issue a
stop work order or halt a data center
project?
>> That's a good question. I would tell you
couple things that come to mind for me
is uh some zoning violations. We have uh
one that really comes to mind to me is a
one I worked with Austin on on a crypto
miner that was a little bit loud and um
we worked with him to turn the
electricity down till the till the
servers got into uh compliance and uh we
took care of it that way but we could
have turned that site completely off. If
our chief building official finds a code
violation, especially if it has a health
and safety um impact, uh they would
issue a stop work order until that was
resolved uh to his satisfaction. Um, I
don't know. Charles, did you want to add
to that?
>> No, mayor. I think you did a really good
job summarizing there. Um, really all
the the data center developers we've had
in the community, they they're all rule
players. They're asking for inspections
on time, they're following their site
plan, so we're not seeing any any
issues. But if someone wasn't following
a site pen, wasn't following a building
permanent approval, that's when there'd
be uh a potential for what is commonly
known as a red tag or a stop work order
that's placed on that? And we haven't uh
run into those problems.
Thank you. Uh Dan, this one's for you.
Do data centers affect ambient
temperatures? And if so, how far away
from each center? How will that impact
life?
So, let's say you have a flat piece of
land. It's an empty space.
Now, you put a Costco, you put a
distribution center, um you put a data
center, you put a school, you put
anything, anything in which a building
has to have cooling to it. Doesn't
matter what type of building that is,
that building will be hotter than an
empty flat piece of land. It's kind of,
you know, simple physics. That's sort of
how it works. So I think this idea that
data centers are creating this ambient
heat that is flowing into other
communities. The research is flimsy. You
can take a reading here, take a reading
there, and yet what you're not
distinguishing is that is a parcel of
land that has a building, you know. So
what doesn't matter what type of
building it is, it's concrete, it's
mechanical systems. They're the same
type of things that go into every type
of large facility. So the question
really becomes do we want to develop
these pieces of land? Should we have
that? Is that going to be affecting
things? It's not a data center specific
question. So I just I I would challenge
folks to think about this to say let's
think about this in terms of any type of
building, any type of development and
whether or not there's research to
support that because there isn't. you
know, you go out, it's it's easy to say,
well, data centers, uh, data centers,
data centers, data centers, but if you
have any type of building, there will be
heat that happens with it. Um, and so we
need to think about these things
holistically. We can't just be looking
at one type of facility and say that's
the problem.
>> Thank you very much. Uh, this is for
Jonathan and Dan. What happens to a site
when a data center closes? How is it
remediated? And I think basically
they're asking when it's retired
what what happens.
>> Uh I'll let you know when I see it. Um I
>> was going to ask have you ever retired
one? I don't think you have. Right.
>> Not not to my knowledge. I I mean I
haven't been involved the whole 20 years
we've been doing data centers, but I I
haven't seen it yet. Uh to my
experience. I think fundamentally it's
important to note that when Microsoft
data centers makes a decision to invest
in the community, this is a hundreds of
millions if not billion dollars
investment. This is a long-term
commitment to the community that we will
be there for the long term. It's not
simply about hey this is going to be
obsolete. We have heard how the demand
for digital services is only increasing.
You know, Dan had a good stat. The
amount of data that we're going to
generate and need to store over the next
five years is twice as much has been
generated over the past 10 years. And as
we all incorporate more and more devices
in our lives, that is only going to
continue to accelerate.
What that means is facilities like this
are going to need to exist for a long
long long time. The technology will
evolve but the need for these facilities
will not. Microsoft constantly invests
in these facilities whether at the
server level, at the system level or at
the building level because this
commitment to the community is driven by
a number of different factors. We've
talked about a several of them, but core
among them, access to energy, Wyoming's
uniquely positioned there. Access to
fiber, once again, Cheyenne in
particular, Wyoming in general, uniquely
positioned there. Quality workforce,
including IBW, the electricians here,
the operations folks we have here,
partnership we have with Larmy Community
Colleges, otherwise the this is a unique
place. It's very well suited to support
data center operations not simply now
not simply over the past 15 20 years but
going ahead decades so I don't see a
time when these facilities will be
retired they will be reborn over and
over again
>> yeah and you know this is essentially a
building with power running into it I
think let's not overthink exactly what
is what is going on here. You know, this
is not a building with highly, you know,
toxic amounts of chemicals and things
like that that it's handling on a
regular basis. This is a building with
power running into it. Um, and as long
as demand is there, there's an absolute
need for these facilities. These
facilities aren't going away anytime
soon. And yeah, we haven't seen a
facility decommissioned, if you will, is
is the term I hear a lot. Um and really
what's important too is that companies
like Microsoft but every company just as
an an electric utility is trying to plan
right and forecast demand because we
want to get it right. We want to make
sure we build the right amount of
infrastructure. If we overbuild then we
have a risk of stranded cost. If we
underbuild then we can't get power to
people and businesses in a timely
manner. Just like that a data center
company is evaluating demand. How do we
make sure that we don't build it
overbuild digital infrastructure but we
also don't underbuild it? We got to
rightsize that. I think there's a lot of
fear out there that says we're going to
build these buildings and we don't need
them in 10 years. That's simply not
going to be the case because the real,
you know, the big legit companies like
Microsoft are right sizing the demand
that they see in the marketplace
probably on a daily basis, you know,
just to make sure that they are
investing their billions of dollars
wisely. Um, and we see buildings in
Northern Virginia. I think there's a
data center in the old America online
headquarters. There's a building in
downtown Denver, which is where all the
telecom lines used to come in, but now
it's fiber lines that's been repurposed
into a data center. Uh we see the old
Sears headquarter in Chicago being a
data centers, a Lexus Nexus warehouse in
Ohio becoming a data center. What we see
is that data centers are actually giving
life back into these old facilities that
have significant amounts of
infrastructure already into them. So
it's just another way that we are seeing
how data centers come in and are you
know building out the infrastructure
that we need doing it with existing
resources but building out appropriately
and utilizing what's there to ensure
that we rightsize this investment.
>> Thank you both. Uh this question is for
Betsy Jonathan and Truit. We're going to
get you involved here.
>> I'm I'm going to pass my minutes on to
Truit.
>> Okay. Very good. Thank you. The question
is what type of jobs at these centers
are here are are for people here in
Cheyenne Wyoming to build the centers
people are worried these jobs will be
outsourced.
>> Wow. So I've been waiting patiently I
guess. Um so yeah I'm part of the
electricians union here in town. Um
we've got over 200 people on a on a meta
site. We're starting to man up a
Microsoft site. Um, they're highly
skilled, highly professional people
coming. Um, we're we're growing our
apprenticeship tenfold. I mean, we're
looking at powerhouse days back in the
70s, 80s with our apprentichip growth.
Um, I think this will be the the largest
class that we've put forth um in in a
long time. uh you know with Cheyenne
we've always seen the booms with the
growth with the missile silos back in
the 50s60s turn that into the power
plant days in the in the late 70s 80s
and now we're into the technology boom
that we're seeing today and it is just
it's mindboggling how fast these are
going. Um the the demand for skilled
labor on them is just amazing. Um the
laborers they're they're booming. the
plumbers and pipe fitters. I think this
is their largest apprenticeship class in
this area in a long time, which is good.
If you need a plumber here before too
long, they'll be able to help you out
there. Same with us. We'll be able to
help you guys out with with service work
as well. Um, and then the long-term jobs
afterwards, the maintenance jobs, we
represent Microsoft's West Campus with
uh their maintenance contract out there.
Those guys are making good wages. that's
negotiated. Uh they love it. Um we were
actually trying to hire more out there,
I believe. So, um if if if you know
anybody that has like wants to get in
the trades, now is a really good time to
do it. I've been working with Larry
County School District 1 and the Trades
Academy and the Metallica Scholarship. I
wish they were here to brag about that.
Um we've been able to get those kids
going through our pipeline, getting them
into the apprenticeship programs where
they want to get into a trade. Um, just
had a kid in the office yesterday kind
of debating on whether or not sheet
metal or electrician. I told him, "Well,
you can put tin together or you can put
wires together. Take your pick." Um, I
think he's going to come our direction
after we we had a good conversation. So,
the opportunities are here and and I'm
really enjoying putting people to work.
That's a great example. A as part of our
community first AI uh infrastructure
pledge. We we are committing to creating
jobs locally and we've been living that
commitment in Wyoming for a number of
years as has been touched upon. We've
been here for 14 years. We've been under
kind of con continuous construction for
12 of those 14. That means these
construction jobs that folks think of as
short-term jobs are careers. And our
goal is to be here for another
number of decades and for be building
out our facility over that time frame.
Uh we are as was touched upon earlier um
moving through the process with the city
right now to evaluate an expansion of
our operations here. Our goal is to um
continue to plan uh and design that with
the city, start working with Black Hills
Energy, with BOPU on the infrastructure
and then to be building that out over a
long term. We our we recognize it's a
larger site. That's not going to happen
overnight. That site will be built over
10 15 plus years providing continuous
jobs for construction. Let's talk about
the operations side. On the operations
side, um, everyone has a different
model. Microsoft's model is about 50
employees per building. Those include IT
operations, critical infrastructure,
uh, security, etc. on the operations
side and on the construction side. We've
talked a little bit about it, but it's
not simply IBW and the terrific workers
there. Plumbers still HVAC, all these
trades are coming in and they are, you
know, settling here because they know
the work is going to be here for a long,
long time. They're also having local
folks who are entering the trades. We
actually go into the high schools here
and talk uh with our trades folks about
the opportunities on the construction
side. We also talk about the
opportunities on the data center
operations side. We've created a
partnership with Laram uh County
Community College, the data center
academy that has seen over a thousand
people go through that academy come out
with a certificate become eligible to
work for a company like Microsoft or
quite frankly any company uh
organization that is running a data
center whether that's military whether
that's state whether it's private or
whether it's the data centers
themselves. It's very effective system.
It works in cooperation as kind of the
next level for the folks who aren't
being attracted to the incredible
well-paying jobs that are available in
the trades here. And we are seeing
people here take advantage of those
opportunities whether it's early career,
mid-career, late career um in all these
different sectors.
>> Thank you. We're getting towards the end
here. Uh this question is for Mayor
Collins, Betsy, and Truit. The question
is, I see so much oppositions to data
centers lately, but I don't understand
it because I see new industry and jobs.
Can you tell me more about the benefits
to the state and to the community?
>> I really love that question. Thank you.
So, just in the last uh few weeks, we
did the ribbon cutting for the gutter
bins. Um the data centers paid for
gutter bins. What these are, they're
baskets that we put in our our drains.
so that when the garbage runs down, it
gets captured there and doesn't go into
our creeks to try to keep our creeks
healthier. Um, we just completed our
2,000th uh tree for rooted in Cheyenne.
Um, Microsoft has paid for hundreds of
those trees um so that we can uh
recreate our urban forest. Um, you just
heard about the uh Larry County
Community College uh data center academy
uh program where they have a thousand
graduates. Um was a week or two ago I
attended a meta uh grant program where
they gave 12 grants to 11 different
agencies and it was over a quarter of a
million dollars. They do this on a
regular basis. If you at Fridays on the
plaza we have a new video board there
that u um was part of that grant paid
for a third of it. Um, on Monday, we're
going to approve or accept a $3.5
million gift from Related Digital that
is going to be it was the last piece we
needed to build 184 million or 184 unit
affordable housing um, uh, complex that
we're going to break ground later this
week, a month or early next month. Um,
Boys and Girls Clubs received over a
million dollars from uh, data centers.
And I could go on and on about all the
different things that um that data
centers have done for us, but I ask you
a quick question. What is Wyoming's
largest export? I think most of us would
say that's uh that's energy or it's u
it's our minerals, right? But for me, I
think what our our largest export is our
kids. Um 67% of our kids leave the state
of Wyoming before they're 30 years old
and very few of them ever come back. uh
we all have a one or two stories, but
they leave it and they and we're
spending billions of dollars educating
our children here in Wyoming and um we
send them through K through 12 to LC the
University of Wyoming wherever we go and
then we send them to Denver and we send
them to Salt Lake City and Fort Collins.
Uh we send them to Boise, Idaho, and uh
that frustrates the heck out of me when
I look at data centers. Um, Chief Amber
Ash and I went to uh we toured Meta a
few months ago. And as we were walking
through the building, I had five kids
who graduated from the high school that
I went to. Uh, that came up to me that
left 15, 20 years ago. They were living
in Portland. They were living in
Seattle. Uh, they came back. They
brought their families back to Wyoming
because these data center jobs were the
kind of jobs they were looking for. And
so for me, it's giving kids a choice.
Um, it's if they want to go to Fort
Collins, if they want to go to Denver
and live in a more urban thing, I get
that. But I think what's happening right
now is I don't think kids feel like they
have a choice. If they want to have a
quality job, they they've got to leave.
And and so I love that. I I look at um
our tax base. You know, the legislature
cut property taxes 25% for residential,
50% for old guys like me. Um, and when
you look across the state right now,
there's 4H programs closing. There's
libraries either closing or or reducing
their hours. But in Larry County, we
haven't had to do that. We've been so
blessed that our sales our property
taxes have uh have stayed stable. And
that's because I think a lot of what
happened with the data centers. And then
I talked about it earlier, but you can
see the impact to uh uh our sales tax
and our and our franchise fees. Um,
that's allowing us to do some things
that we uh we weren't sure we were going
to do. When I became mayor 5 years ago,
today we have uh 12 more firefighters
than we did before. We've got another
fire station that we're able to man. We
have 10 more police officers on the
road. We have more uh things like the
gymnastics facility. We actually own
gymnasiums for the first time. So, these
dollars are helping us create uh some of
the quality of life things that we have
not been able to do in the past. And I
think the ability to do that in the
future is even going to be more. So for
me, um, that's Holly to answer that
question. Sir,
>> I'm going to try to be brief, but two
things I want to point out. If you
didn't read Governor Gordon's executive
order, data centers the Wyoming way, I
think that's going to be really
important for you to get a a copy of and
take a look because one of the things
that we do in Wyoming is we do business
a certain way. And I think Jonathan and
Dan alluded to it and we do it a lot
differently than most places do. So
please take a look at that. But the
question was, I see so much opposition
to data centers lately, but I don't
understand because I see new jobs and
industry. Um, yesterday the governor had
an op-ed uh sent out and uh I want to
quote something from that oped and it's
from uh Fox Business Network and it was
on May 26. US Interior Secretary Doug
Bergam explicitly warned that areas
building out tech infrastructure are
being bombarded with foreign directed
propaganda to try to block these from
being built. I am being bombarded
personally uh not necessarily by Russia
or China as they are alluding to here
but from Bangladesh. So, what I want you
to become is a sophisticated and savvy
user of social media, of the data center
tools that are out there for you to take
pictures of your grandkids. I do it.
I've probably got 10,000 of my grandkids
in the cloud and on my aura frame and
every day they ship me another one and
there they are, you know. So, I probably
have more pictures of my grandkids than
I ever had of my kids. But in any event,
um, for example, when we saw the large
ad in the Wyoming Tribune Eagle, the
full page ad that said no data centers,
no data centers, no data centers, the
paid for by was the people of Wyoming.
And we have yet to this day found out
who that group is and who paid for it.
And that was anonymous. So I would just
ask you to become consumers of
information that asks the question, does
this look real? Is there beachfront
property in Wyoming? So, please please
do that. And the other thing I would say
and I and True's got some great stories
is um please remember that data centers
are people too. They're not buildings.
They're not companies. They're people.
There's people that work in those
places. And I was at a Rotary Club
meeting and we had a woman that was for
the moratorum sitting next to a woman
who was against the moratorum
because one, the woman that was against
the moratorum because her son was able
to move back here and bring her three
grandkids back here to Wyoming because
he got a job at a data center. She would
have to be traveling to go see her
grandkids if it wasn't for the data
center economy. the woman that was uh
for the moratorum heard that and it
finally clicked. And so now there's two
people that know each other on opposite
sides of the issue, but now they're
there to support each other. And so I
think that is the way we do things in
Wyoming. We have conversations. We
consider other people's positions, but
the most important thing we do is we
consider the facts. So Truit, tell us
some great stories about the benefits.
tell us about those young people and
those old people and those mid-career
people.
>> Yeah, no pressure there. Uh
and I'm the last one between us and the
door. So, uh you know, part of our
organization, we're trying to do uh
quarterly community activities. Um you
know, for the longest time, we've had
the adopt a highway uh behind the
Albertsons there on Persing. And uh I
think about once a year it always got
brought up at one of the meetings if we
were ever going to go do anything with
it. And with all these young kids coming
in, they they've taken the charge and
the initiative and we're we're working
on that. We've worked with Rooted and
Cheyenne. Um being on the dig teams. Um
it's our way to try and give back to the
community. We do food drive uh holiday
food drive every year now. Uh, I mean,
realistically, if it wasn't for the
community and and their their support
and outreach, uh, you know, we wouldn't
be where we are today with everything.
So, uh, I I hope that's a wonderful
enough story, uh, for you guys.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor.
>> You know, there's just a couple more
things that came to mind as I was
sitting here. Um, you know, Austin
talked about it earlier. The data
centers are helping keep our electric
rates lower. uh and that they're
creating the redundancy and the
reliability for our system. They're
doing the upgrades so that u our utility
is one of the best in the country. And
then I I think about like the Bison
Business Park. It's down south off of
South Gley Highway and they had to run
what three miles of water and sewer
lines to it. Well, bringing that three
miles of water and sewer lines just
opened up three miles of land for future
housing and other developments that
could happen that would not have
happened but for the data center coming.
And I think about the meta uh data
center on the that part of town. By
bringing all the water and sewer there,
we have the High Plains business park
now. It's a 2100 acre business park.
That was going to be a real challenge to
develop because getting water and sewer
there was going to be millions of
dollars. But Meta brought it to the
corner to the edge of their property. So
now we'll be able to expand that and
that should allow that development to
happen much sooner bringing other
quality jobs to uh to Cheyenne and to
Wyoming. So, I see lots of benefits that
come from data centers.
>> Thank you all very much. Um, we're we're
at the end of our questions. I want to
give everybody an opportunity to to add
a final thought if you'd like to. Dan,
you want to start?
>> Yeah. I I I've heard a lot lately about
not everything can be sunshine and
roses, right? You're you're telling me
all the good stuff here, you know, but
it can't all be 100% perfect. Um, and I
think it isn't 100% perfect. We know
from the the discharge issue, right,
that there are there there are and there
can be issues with with any kind of
development. I think what's been very
clear up here is that you have
commitments from private industry, from
utilities, from city officials to do
this responsibly and to work through
these issues because they they happen
and they come up. You know, there are
data centers that may have a sound
issue. Okay, let's be responsive and
let's figure that out. Um, and I think
that's just one thing I want to
emphasize and leave everyone with here
is that yes, there's nothing that can be
100% perfect. There are a lot of good
things. There will be challenges and
there will be challenges in the future
as we face important planning
discussions around water, around
infrastructure, around long-term
economic development. But as long as we
can all work together and focus on the
practical solutions that work and make
the adjustments necessary, you know, we
can do this to the benefit um of
Cheyenne and to the benefit of all
Wyoming. So, I just want to make sure I
leave you with that point. There's a lot
of great happening here and I
understand, you know, not everything can
be sunshine and roses, but we can do it.
We can make it all sunshine and roses as
long as we just address this practically
and I think with sound facts and sound
data.
>> Anyone else? A final thought, Truett.
>> Yeah. So, real quick, I mean, we're
we're we're talking about everything all
fun and and everything. Um, another fun
little fact that I've seen with all all
the building trades is these apprentices
being able to buy firsttime home, be
able to get out of their parents'
basement in their 20s. Um, you know, I I
was fortunate enough and bought a house
15 years ago before everything started
really going up in cost. I don't know if
my wife and I could do that today
without, you know, a decent paying job
with with with what what's available out
there right now. So, uh, yeah, it's a
really cool thing uh, have an apprentice
walk in the door and say, you know, hey,
I'm closing on the house today. Uh,
we're going to have a barbecue in a
weekend or two. Come over and say hi.
So, uh, yeah, that's kind of kind of
cool to see that for for a while.
>> Thank you. Mayor Collins, do you have
something?
>> Yeah, I would like to pay a compliment
to the board of public utilities. I uh
was elected along with Mr. Crave, we
were both elected to the city council
November of 2000. And at that time, data
centers or not data centers, uh, the
city of Cheyenne used about what 14,500
acre feet of water and today we use
around 12,000. So, I just grabbed my
phone. I did the quick calculation.
That's 650 million gallons of water that
we use less today than we did back then.
And that puts the Board of Public
Utilities in a kind of a tough
situation. Since the year 2000, if you
think about what does it cost us to run
our homes, what things that are more
expensive, the pipe that they're, you
know, we have hundreds of miles of water
pipe and sewer pipe, things like that.
They have to replace those pipes. And we
have a a program that we do that every
year, but it's gotten so much more
expensive. but we're selling so much
less water. It's it's really it's it's a
challenge for them. So, the truth is the
Board of Public Utilities needs to sell
more water, but they're saying no to
people who don't want to use closed loop
systems because it's the right thing to
do. And uh because it's it's a
responsible way for us to use our water.
Uh but the the truth of the matter is we
need to sell another thousand 2,000 acre
feet of water to give them the resources
they need to continue with the
maintenance programs that we have.
Otherwise, we're going to end up like,
and I don't want to pick on a company
like uh community like Rollins, but you
know, they had a a major disaster. Their
water system completely failed and and
years later, they're still struggling to
get that thing back on track. We have to
do that maintenance. We have to keep up
on our system, which means they have to
sell water because if they don't sell
water, they don't have the resources.
They can't they can't do that without
the money that they get from selling the
water. So, I just want to pay them a
compliment for doing the right thing.
Uh, and also to our residents for using
water really efficiently. We're doing
the right thing with our water. It's
just costing them a little bit in the
process.
Anyone else?
Okay. On behalf of the city of Cheyenne,
thank you all for taking the time to
join us and participate in this
important community conversation. I
would also like to extend a sincere
thanks to our panelists for sharing
their time, expertise, and perspectives
today. Please join me in giving them a
well-deserved round of applause.
If you would like to learn more about
data center development in Cheyenne,
additional information and resources are
available on the city of Cheyenne's
website at cheyen city.org
uhdataenters and on the leads website at
cheyenle.org
yhy-enata-corers.
Thank you again for attending. We
appreciate it. Have a great evening.